A Finding Aid to the Elsie Driggs Papers, 1924-1979, in the Archives of American Art aaa.drigelsi
Archives of American Art
Elsie Driggs papers
1924-1979
aaa.drigelsi
Archives of American Art
0.2 Linear feet
The scattered papers of New York City painter Elsie Driggs date from 1924 to 1979 and measure 0.2 linear feet. Included are correspondence, writings by Driggs, personal business records, printed materials, and portrait and family photographs.
Driggs, Elsie, 1898-
Scope and Contents note
The scattered papers of New York City painter Elsie Driggs date from 1924 to 1979 and measure 0.2 linear feet. Included are correspondence, writings by Driggs, personal business records, printed materials, and portrait and family photographs.
Correspondence includes letters from the Baltimore Museum of Art, Adelyn Breeskin, Alexander Brook, Edward Bruce, Columbus Gallery of Fine Arts, dealer Charles Daniel, Heckscher Museum, Montclair Art Museum, Munson-Williams-Proctor Institute, Newark Musuem, Cynthia Sanford, Francis Steegmuller, Maurice Stern, Jenny Strauss, Walker Art Center, Wichita State University, and Yale University Art Gallery.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 5 series.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1924-1979 (3 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Writings and Notes, circa 1960 (2 folders; Box 1)
Series 3: Personal Business Records, 1964-1979 (1 folder; Box 1)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1964-1978 (1 folder; Box 1)
Series 5: Photographs, 1925-1961 (4 folders; Box 1)
Biographical/Historical note
Elsie Driggs (1898-1992) was a New York City Precisionist painter, curator, and art critic.
Born in Connecticut, Elsie Driggs attended the Art Students League in New York City. She traveled through Italy where she found inspiration from the works of Piero Della Francesca. After settling in New York City, she became active in the Precisionist movement, which reacted to skyscrapers and other modern building projects. Later in her career, she painted watercolors under the federal Public Works of Art project. Driggs was married to fellow artist Lee Gatch.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Portions of the papers were microfilmed on reel D160. The microfilm is available for interlibrary loan but researchers are advised that the microfilm does not reflect the current order of the papers and is incomplete.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Elsie Driggs donated her papers to the Archives of American Art in several accretions between 1963 and 1980.
Related Archival Materials note
The Archives of American Art holds an oral history interview with Elsie Driggs conducted by Francine Tyler October 30-December 5, 1985.
Baltimore Museum of Art; Breeskin, Adelyn Dohme, 1896-; Brook, Alexander, 1898-1980; Bruce, Edward, 1879-1943; Columbus Gallery of Fine Arts.; Daniel, Charles, 1878-1971; Heckscher Museum; Montclair Art Museum; Munson-Williams-Proctor Institute.; Newark Museum; Sanford, Cynthia Holthusen; Steegmuller, Francis, 1906-1994; Sterne, Maurice, 1878-1957; Walker Art Center; Wichita State University.; Yale University. Art Gallery.; Photographs; Women painters -- New York (State) -- New York
- Correspondence, 1924-1979; Series 1; 3 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Found is scattered correspondence, most of which references specific works of art by Elsie Driggs and Lee Gatch. Correspondents include: Baltimore Museum of Art, Adelyn Breeskin, Alexander Brook, Edward Bruce, Columbus Gallery of Fine Arts, Charles Daniel, Heckscher Museum, Montclair Art Museum, Munson-Williams-Proctor Institute Newark Musuem, Cynthia Sanford, Francis Steegmuller, Jenny Strauss, Walker Art Center, Wichita State University, and Yale University Art Gallery. Letters from Charles Daniel includes sales information. Letters from Edward Bruce urge Driggs to write her congressman to support the Public Works of Art Project, and refuse her payment of a loan.
  - 1920s-1940s, 1924-1938; circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1950s-1960s, 1953-1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1970s, 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Writings and Notes, circa 1960; Series 2; 2 Folders Box 1
  Found are two short stories by Elsie Driggs.
  - "The Stones of Lee Gatch", circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "In Search of Piero Dela Francesca", circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Personal Business Records, 1964-1979; Series 3; 1 Folders Box 1
  Found are two receipts for the loan and consignment of works of art by Elsie Driggs from the Provincetown Art Association and Sotheby's, respectively.
  - Consignment and Loan Receipts, 1964-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Printed Material, 1964-1978; Series 4; 1 Folders Box 1
  Found are exhibition announcements and catalogs for solo and group shows of Elsie Diggs.
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1964-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Photographs, 1925-1961; Series 5; 4 Folders Box 1
  Found are portraits and snapshots of Elsie Driggs, family, friends, and homes. A photograph of friends is of the Anticoli group, including Maurice Sterne, Edward Bruce, Elsa Schmid Neumann, Louise Maloney, Gertrude Tienser-Willie, and Mario Topi.
  - Elsie Diggs, 1925-1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Elsie Diggs and Family, circa 1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Elsie Diggs and Friends, circa 1925 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Homes, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)